## Hong Lu

Contact Information Phone: (603) 277-0552 www: http://honglu.github.io/ E-mail: hong.lu.mail@gmail.com

Research Interests Areas: ubiquitous computing, machine learning, sensing system, context awareness.

I am a senior research scientist in Intel Labs working on developing sensing systems and machine learning techniques that collect and reason about complex sensor data. I have over 10 years of experience in applying AI to the areas of human behavior modeling, context understanding, and recently high volume manufacturing. As part of my research, I create mobile systems that sense, inform, assist, and influence people. My work has been productized in various Intel commercial products and deployed in Intel manufacturing facilities. I published my research findings in top-tier pervasive computing and machine learning conferences. My current h-index is 26 and I have over 8000 citations according to Google Scholar.

**EDUCATION** 

Ph.D., Computer Science, Dartmouth College Hanover NH, USA

Sep. 2006 - May. 2012

• Thesis: Smartphone Sensing and Inference of Human Behavior and Context

M.S., Computer Science, Tianjin Unviersity Tianiin, China

Sep.2003 - Jun. 2006

• Thesis: An Enhanced Weighted Clustering Algorithm for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks

B.S., Computer Science, Tianjin Unviersity Tianjin, China

Sep. 1999 - Jun. 2003

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Research Scientist

May. 2012 - present

Intel Labs, Santa Clara, CA

My research in Intel Labs is currently focused on pushing AI to mobile devices and to Intel manufacturing process. I develop systems to collect and analysis complex data with application scenarios spanning from low-power mobile devices to complex industrial manufacturing environments. I built prototype applications to make inferences about human activities, context, social interactions, and life routines. These systems provide a rich understanding of people's everyday life and create mobile technologies for better user experience. I also work on develop ML systems to see through large volume of manufacturing data to improve manufacturing efficiency and product quality.

#### Research Intern

Jun. 2010 - Sep. 2010

Microsoft Research, Redmond WA

I studied continuous audio sensing and speaker identification on heterogeneous multiprocessor mobile phone architecture. I implemented a prototype on HTC HD2 smart phone with LittleRock sensor board. One patent is filed and the SpeakerSense paper accepted by Pervasive 2011 (Best Paper Nominee).

#### Research Intern

Jun. 2009 - Dec. 2009

Nokia Research Center, Palo Alto, CA

I designed and implemented Jigsaw, a robust context/activity recognition engine for smart phones using the on-board accelerometer, microphone and GPS sensors. I developed a daily activity tracking and logging application with the Jigsaw engine on Nokia N900 smartphone. Three IPs and one patent are filed and Jigsaw paper accepted by SenSys 2010.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

According to Google Scholar, I have over 8000 citations and my h-index is 26. For a complete list of my publications, please visit my google scholar page.

# SELECTED PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Associate Editor of ACM, Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT) Journal.
- Registrations Chair of The 15th ACM International Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications, and Services (Mobisys 2017), Niagara Falls, NY, USA
- Program committee (TPC) member of The 16th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks (IPSN 2017), Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.
- Program committee (PC) member of The 2015 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp 2015), Umeda, Osaka, Japan.
- Posters and Demos Chair of The 12th International Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications, and Services (MobiSys 2014), Bretton Woods, NH, USA.
- Technical program committee (TPC) member of MobiSense, in conjunction with Pervasive 2011, San Francisco, USA.

### SELECTED NEWS AND PRESS

- Your phone can recognize you by the way you walk, VBNews, September 2013.
- o Smartphone that feels your strain, NewScientist, August 2012.
- o Voice-Stress Software Is Put to the Test, PhysOrgandACMTech, August 2012.
- The Cyborg in us all, the NYTimes Magazine, September 2011.
- Nokia toys with context-aware smartphone settings switch, Jigsaw provides better context for apps like this, Engadget, Nov 2010.
- o Smartphone app monitors your every move, NewScientist, 26 November 2010.
- o Mobile Phone Mind Control, TechnologyReview, March, 2010.
- o Cell phones that listen and learn, TechnologyReview, June, 2009.
- o Cell Phones That Learn the Sounds of Your Life, Slashdot, July, 2009.

EXPERTISE

Programming Language: JAVA, Python, MATLAB, C.

Operating Systems: Linux, Android